In this video,
I review the health
benefits of millets,
including its potential
impact on diabetes.
Check it out.
"Is Millet Healthy?"
Millets are highly nutritious
but vastly ignored
as a main source of food, primarily
due to lack of awareness.
You’ve heard of “ancient grains”?
Millets ain’t messin’ around,
arguably the ﬁrst grains
cultivated by humankind,
not just dating back 5,000 years,
but maybe 10,000 years.
Why the plural, millets?
Talk about lack of awareness!
I had no idea that millet wasn’t
the name of a specific grain.
Millet is just a generic term
that doesn’t just apply to a bunch
of different species but to a
bunch of totally different plants.
There are so-called major
and minor millets.
There’s pearl millet, which is what
I think most people think of
as millet, but then there are proso,
foxtail, and finger millets
which are all completely different grains.
They look similar,
but they’re not the same.
Fiber is one of the main things we’re
looking for in a whole grain,
and kodo millet is like off the charts.
But compared to other grains,
finger and foxtail millet
also beat out the bunch, though note
that what most people think of
as millet is really on the low side.
But looking at the polyphenol
content, even plain millet
beats out the other grains,
including sorghum,
which I previously hyped
for its polyphenol content.
But again, kodo millet
seems to win the day.
Total antioxidant-wise, though, kodo
and finger millet are comparably high.
Nutrition-wise, finger millet is said
to have eight times more calcium
than other grains, but it looks
to me more like ten times more,
just off the charts, and three
times as much calcium as milk.
Some of the millets are
exceptionally high in iron as well.
Regular millet is high, but barnyard millet
has like five times more iron than steak.
Okay, so it’s nutritious, but what
about specific potential health beneﬁts?
In the medical literature,
you’ll read things like this:
Millets may prevent cardiovascular
disease by reducing triglycerides
in hyperlipidemic rats.
Who cares (other than
perhaps pet owners)
whether a food reduces
cardiovascular disease in rodents?
There was that epidemiological
study in China that found
lower esophageal cancer mortality
rates in areas that ate
more millet and sorghum,
compared to corn and wheat,
but that may have been more
due to avoiding a contaminating
carcinogenic fungus than from
benefit in the millet itself.
Studies show millets may be effective
against cancer cell proliferation,
in a petri dish, with kodo and
proso millet rapidly inhibiting
cancer cell growth compared to
pearl or foxtail millet,
knocking down the growth of cancer
cells, but leaving normal cells alone,
reducing the growth of
colon cancer cells
as well as human breast cancer,
and human liver cancer cells,
potentially also helping
to prevent metastases
by inhibiting cancer cell migration.
My patients are neither pets nor
petri dishes, though, and to date,
there have been no clinical
cancer trials with millet.
Are there any unique
health-promoting attributes?
Finger millet is supposedly known
for its health benefits,
such as blood sugar-lowering,
cholesterol-lowering,
and anti-ulcer characteristics.
But the anti-ulcer study they cite
just noted that some of the areas
with a low incidence of ulcers
also happened to be eating millet,
but that’s far from establishing
cause-and-effect.
And the cholesterol-
lowering study they cite?
It explored what happens when
you take tail tendons from rats
and soak them in sugar
and millet. What?!
But the blood-sugar lowering
benefits are legit.
Apart from the fact that
millets don’t contain gluten,
which is good for the 1% or 2%
of people with celiac disease
or non-celiac gluten sensitivity,
millets can also be exploited
in the management of type 2
diabetes due to their blood sugar
lowering properties, as reported
by several studies on millets
and millet-based foods in actual
people, which we’ll cover next.
How does millet come to
the help of diabetics?
A substantial portion of the starch
in millet is resistant starch,
meaning resistant to digestion
in our small intestine,
so providing a bounty for
the good bugs in our colon.
Here’s how the various millets do,
all way more than more common
grains like rice or wheat, but
proso and kodo millet lead the pack.
What’s going on? The protein
matrix in millet not only acts
as a physical barrier but actually
also partially sequesters
your starch-munching enzyme,
and the millet polyphenols
also can act as starch
blockers in and of themselves.
Millet also has markedly slower
stomach emptying times
than other starchy foods. If you eat
white rice, boiled potatoes,
or pasta, your stomach takes
about an hour to digest it,
before starting to slowly
dump it into your intestines,
and two or three hours
to empty about half-way.
Whereas you eat sorghum or
millet, and stomach emptying
doesn’t even start
until two or three hours
and may take five hours
to empty even halfway.
Note this was for both
a thick millet porridge
and for just millet couscous.
Since the non-viscous millet
couscous meal was also equally slow
in emptying, this suggests that
there may just be something
about millet itself that
helps slow stomach emptying,
which should blunt the
blood sugar spike.
But you don’t know...until
you put it to the test.
And indeed, millet caused about a
20% lower surge in blood sugar
than the same amount of
carbs in the form of rice.
Remember how excited I was to show
you how it only took the body
like half the insulin to handle
sorghum compared to a grain like corn?
Well, millet did even better.
Give a group of prediabetics only
about three-quarters of a cup
of millet a day, and within six
weeks their insulin resistance
dropped so much their
prediabetic fasting blood sugars
turned into non-
prediabetic blood sugars.
This so-called “self-
controlled” clinical trial,
the same subjects before and
after, is just a sneaky way
of saying an uncontrolled trial.
There was no control group
that didn’t add the millet
or added something else.
And we know just being in
a study under scrutiny
can cause people to eat
better in other ways.
So, we don’t know what role,
if any, the millet itself played.
What we need is a randomized,
controlled crossover trial
where the same people eat
both a millet-containing
and non-millet containing diet
and see which works better.
And here we go! A randomized,
crossover study having
hundreds of patients both do an
American Diabetes Association-type
diet with and without about one and
one-third cup of millet every day,
and… the millet-based diet
lowered hemoglobin A1C levels,
meaning an improvement in long-term
blood sugar control,
along with some side benefits
like lowering cholesterol.
The target for good blood
sugar control recommended
by the American Diabetes Association
is an A1C less than 7.
They started out at 8.37, but
after a few months on millet,
dropped it to an average of 6.77.
Is it just because they lost
weight or something?
No, suggesting that it was an
effect specific to the millet.
But they didn’t just give millet.
They mixed the millet with
split black lentils and spices,
and we know from
dozens of randomized,
controlled experimental trials in
people with and without diabetes
that the consumption of pulses
(meaning beans, split peas,
chickpeas, or lentils) can
improve long-term measures
of blood sugar control like A1C levels.
So, while the researchers conclude
that millets have the potential
for a protective role in
the management of diabetes,
a more accurate conclusion might
be a mix of millet and lentils
can be protective, though hey,
maybe the spices helped too.
They didn’t say which ones they
used, and I couldn’t get ahold
of the authors, but a similar study
done by one of the same researchers
included about a tablespoon a day of
a mixture of fenugreek, coriander,
cumin, and black pepper, with a fifth
spice, perhaps cinnamon or turmeric.